<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>visibilityspots - other</title><link href="https://visibilityspots.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://visibilityspots.github.io/blog/feeds/other.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://visibilityspots.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2020-03-31T21:00:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Linux &amp; Open-Source enthusiast | Scouting | Longboarding</subtitle><subtitle>Linux &amp; Open-Source enthusiast | Scouting | Longboarding</subtitle><entry><title>Plane spotting on a nomad cluster</title><link href="https://visibilityspots.github.io/blog/planespotting.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-31T21:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-03-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Jan</name></author><id>tag:visibilityspots.github.io,2020-03-31:/blog/planespotting.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some weeks ago I upgraded my plane spotting setup by moving my antenna to the &lt;a href="https://visibilityspots.github.io/blog/piaware.html"&gt;roof&lt;/a&gt;. It was worth every single effort I've made into it. My stats are rocking ever since. Until the corona crisis halted almost every airline to standstill..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gave me some time to thinker about my setup, and for some weird coincidence &lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye"&gt;Mike&lt;/a&gt; did create a series of docker containers like I was thinking about to implement. I have one pi connected to the USB device which captures the ADB radio signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the current situation it also feeds the flightaware service since I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some weeks ago I upgraded my plane spotting setup by moving my antenna to the &lt;a href="https://visibilityspots.github.io/blog/piaware.html"&gt;roof&lt;/a&gt;. It was worth every single effort I've made into it. My stats are rocking ever since. Until the corona crisis halted almost every airline to standstill..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gave me some time to thinker about my setup, and for some weird coincidence &lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye"&gt;Mike&lt;/a&gt; did create a series of docker containers like I was thinking about to implement. I have one pi connected to the USB device which captures the ADB radio signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the current situation it also feeds the flightaware service since I used the docker container for piaware. So I wanted to split those up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lucky for me Mike did some great work by creating a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye/docker-readsb"&gt;readsb&lt;/a&gt; container which only captures the signals and can be provides them to a port which can be easily consumed by services which feeds the positions towards a specific service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike did a great effort on that part too and crafted several docker images which are able to consume an external beast host to provide the messages towards the services;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye/docker-piaware"&gt;flightaware&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye/docker-flightradar24"&gt;flightradar24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye/docker-adsbexchange"&gt;adsbexchange&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye/docker-radarbox"&gt;radarbox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye/docker-planefinder"&gt;planefinder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By doing so I could have the pi attached to the USB device dedicated for the readsb container and the other services are consuming other nodes in the nomad cluster to provide the leverage towards upstream. That way I have my setup spread over my whole &lt;a href="../nomad-arm-cluster.html"&gt;nomad&lt;/a&gt; cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which makes it totally future proof and made my day during this lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="other"></category><category term="piaware"></category><category term="flightaware"></category><category term="dump1090"></category><category term="ADB-B"></category><category term="nomad"></category><category term="docker"></category><category term="flight"></category><category term="radar"></category><category term="24"></category><category term="flightradar24"></category><category term="DVB-T"></category><category term="readsb"></category><category term="radarbox"></category><category term="planefinder"></category><category term="adsbexchange"></category></entry><entry><title>Piaware on a nomad cluster</title><link href="https://visibilityspots.github.io/blog/piaware.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-31T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Jan</name></author><id>tag:visibilityspots.github.io,2020-01-31:/blog/piaware.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I stumbled on the &lt;a href="https://flightaware.com/"&gt;flightaware&lt;/a&gt; website and figured out you could capture radio signals from an airplane using a DVB-T dongle which can be bought for about EUR 15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this really triggered me to start monitoring planes above our head I bought myself such a device, hooked it up to a raspberry pi zero, installed the piaware software and started grabbing the messages and pushing the compiled positions through flightaware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through time I managed to upgrade my home lab towards a &lt;a href="../nomad-arm-cluster.html"&gt;nomad cluster&lt;/a&gt;. So I migrated my piaware setup to a nomad node and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I stumbled on the &lt;a href="https://flightaware.com/"&gt;flightaware&lt;/a&gt; website and figured out you could capture radio signals from an airplane using a DVB-T dongle which can be bought for about EUR 15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this really triggered me to start monitoring planes above our head I bought myself such a device, hooked it up to a raspberry pi zero, installed the piaware software and started grabbing the messages and pushing the compiled positions through flightaware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through time I managed to upgrade my home lab towards a &lt;a href="../nomad-arm-cluster.html"&gt;nomad cluster&lt;/a&gt;. So I migrated my piaware setup to a nomad node and wrote a &lt;a href="http://www.visibilityspots.com/documents/piaware/nomad.hcl"&gt;nomad job file&lt;/a&gt; to run the docker image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great achievement in my cluster setup regarding the software. For the hardware I initially used a cheap &lt;a href="https://shop.pimoroni.com/products/dvb-t-dongle-ideal-for-ads-b-real-time-plane-tracking"&gt;DVB-T&lt;/a&gt; dongle but I wanted to get more planes and positions so I invested into better gear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After saving enough by skipping the weekly wok days at work I ordered myself a &lt;a href="https://thepihut.com/products/flightaware-1090mhz-ads-b-antenna-66cm-26in"&gt;1090MHz ADS-B N-Type&lt;/a&gt; antenna in combination with the &lt;a href="https://thepihut.com/products/flightaware-pro-stick-plus-usb-sdr-ads-b-receiver"&gt;Flightaware Pro Stick Plus&lt;/a&gt;. To attach the two together I also got myself a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01FVWCKKE/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o02_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1"&gt;15m antenna RF coaxial cable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a first test setup I used a large bamboo pole which I hooked up into the garden as you can see;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bamboo" src="../../images/piaware/bamboo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pi was placed inside of the garage and connected through the wireless network. Unfortunately I had a bad reception and installed a powerline based AP to have a stronger signal in the garage. But this setup suffered from outages from time to time. Causing the pi to lose connection and therefore many messages got lost :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some auto reboots every now and then solved the connectivity issues as a quick 'ducktaped' fix but I wasn't quite happy with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temporary solution of the bamboo stick stood for about a year. Since I didn't wanted (neither was allowed by my girlfriend) to drill a hole through the roof. But I figured out our central heating unit has a fresh air outlet I could use to go to the roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So once equipped with a fancy new pole made by my brother I went for it and installed the antenna on the roof and the pi indoors attached with a network cable instead of the wifi;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="roof" src="../../images/piaware/roof.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then made some time to update the docker container images I used from &lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye/docker-piaware"&gt;Mike Nye&lt;/a&gt; and create some pull requests. Once he merged those I upgraded my nomad job file and running on the latest available stable version of piaware in a container!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move of the antenna together with a stable connection was a big success seen my stats increased significantly! Still the 'Klitsberg' nearby our home is blocking some signals from that direction unfortunately.. Maybe someday I could set up an antenna on top of that hill who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days after I upgraded I figured Mike released a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mikenye/docker-flightradar24"&gt;docker-fr24feed&lt;/a&gt; container image which works in tandem with the docker-piaware one. So I went for it adjusted the nomad job file and now I'm not only pushing messages towards &lt;a href="https://flightaware.com/adsb/stats/user/visibilityspots#stats-89862"&gt;flightaware&lt;/a&gt; but also towards &lt;a href="https://www.flightradar24.com/account/feed-stats/?id=18592"&gt;flightradar24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I still need to figure out is the adjustment of the &lt;a href="https://discussions.flightaware.com/t/thoughts-on-optimizing-gain/44482/2"&gt;gain&lt;/a&gt; which could me bring even better statistics as today :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also since becoming a business member on both platforms because being a feeder could open up a way to an API I could start using to setup my wemos based &lt;a href="https://blog.squix.org/2016/07/esp8266-based-plane-spotter-how-to.html"&gt;plane spotter&lt;/a&gt; in the future!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="other"></category><category term="piaware"></category><category term="flightaware"></category><category term="dump1090"></category><category term="ADB-B"></category><category term="nomad"></category><category term="docker"></category><category term="flight"></category><category term="radar"></category><category term="24"></category><category term="flightradar24"></category><category term="DVB-T"></category><category term="readsb"></category><category term="radarbox"></category><category term="planefinder"></category><category term="adsbexchange"></category></entry></feed>